<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> - Articles</title>
    <description>Make anything fun</description>
    <link>
    </link>
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Lỗi đơn vị kích thước tuyệt đối trong App Inventor</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Bài viết này chỉ ra 1 lỗi sai nghiêm trọng về đơn vị đo sẽ khiến các bạn không kiểu gì hình dung được tại sao mình thiết kế một đằng nhưng App Inventor lại hiển thị một nẻo trong Responsive Mode.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Mar 2020 10:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /absolute-dimension-in-appinventor</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/absolute-dimension-in-appinventor</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Giới thiệu theme Jekyll Mediumish siêu đẹp</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;tính-năng&quot;&gt;Tính năng&lt;/h2&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2020 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /gioi-thieu-theme-mediumish-jekyll</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/gioi-thieu-theme-mediumish-jekyll</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Thêm và chỉnh sửa nội dung Jekyll Post trực tuyến</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Bài viết này sẽ hỗ trợ rất nhiều cho các bạn mới làm quen với viết blog trên Github, và không quen sử dụng Markup Language. Tât nhiên, để vượt qua rào cản ngôn ngữ, bạn cần thêm công cụ. Yên tâm, bạn chẳng cần cài thêm gì trên máy tính đâu, đúng như tiêu đề là sửa trực tuyến nhé! Tất nhiên, bạn vẫn có thể sử dụng giao diện của Github để sửa nội dung file, nhưng giao diện này không thân thiện bằng công cụ mình đề xuất. Công cụ này có tên là Prose.io. Trong bài viết, mình sẽ cập nhật chi tiết về cách sử dụng Prose.io để thêm và chỉnh sửa nội dung blog.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2020 15:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /them-va-chinh-sua-noi-dung-jekyll-post-online</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/them-va-chinh-sua-noi-dung-jekyll-post-online</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>What is an API?</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-an-api-application-programming-interface&quot;&gt;What is an API? (Application Programming Interface)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;API is the acronym for Application Programming Interface, which is a software intermediary that allows two applications to talk to each other. Each time you use an app like Facebook, send an instant message, or check the weather on your phone, you’re using an API.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2020 15:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /what-is-an-api</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/what-is-an-api</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Best Free Image Host Compare In 2020</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;When you want to share a photo or a gallery with friends, family, a message board, or even the entire Internet, an image hosting site is the best way to upload, store, and share your files. However, there are many image hosting sites, all with different features. The best site for you will depend on how many photos you need to upload, how much time you want to spend uploading, and the reason you’re uploading the photos.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2020 15:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /free-image-host-compare</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/free-image-host-compare</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Powerful things you can do with the Markdown editor</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;There are lots of powerful things you can do with the Markdown editor. If you’ve gotten pretty comfortable with writing in Markdown, then you may enjoy some more advanced tips about the types of things you can do with Markdown!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jun 2018 15:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /powerful-things-markdown-editor</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/powerful-things-markdown-editor</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>About Bundler</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gem install bundler&lt;/code&gt; installs the bundler gem through RubyGems. You only need to install it once - not every time you create a new Jekyll project. Here are some additional details:&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 May 2018 10:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /about-bundler</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/about-bundler</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Arduino là cái gì?</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Chắc chắn hồi còn bé xíu, bạn, mình và rất rất nhiều người khác nữa đều thích chơi lắp ráp. Từ những miếng gỗ, hoặc từ những mảnh Lego nhỏ, mình có thể xếp thành bất kì mô hình nào mà mình thấy thích thú. Mình nhớ hồi còn học tiểu học, Lego có về trường mình và tổ chức một cuộc thi lắp ráp nho nhỏ. Tất cả học sinh ngồi chung với nhau, các mảnh Lego được đổ tràn ra và mọi người có quyền chọn lựa bất kì mảnh ghép nào để ráp thành ý tưởng của mình. Và, rất rất nhiều ý tưởng thú vị, cách sắp xếp thú vị được tạo ra từ những mảnh vuông cơ bản ấy: lâu đài, máy bay, tàu, xe tăng, …và rất rất nhiều mô hình tuyệt đẹp khác nữa.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2018 15:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /arduino-la-gi</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/arduino-la-gi</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Options for creating a new site with Jekyll</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll new &amp;lt;PATH&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; installs a new Jekyll site at the path specified (relative to current directory). In this case, Jekyll will be installed in a directory called &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;myblog&lt;/code&gt;. Here are some additional details:&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /options-for-creating-new-site-with-jekyll</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/options-for-creating-new-site-with-jekyll</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Advanced Markdown tips</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;There are lots of powerful things you can do with the Ghost editor&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've gotten pretty comfortable with &lt;a href=&quot;/the-editor/&quot;&gt;all the basics&lt;/a&gt; of writing in Ghost, then you may enjoy some more advanced tips about the types of things you can do with Markdown!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with the last post about the editor, you'll want to be actually editing this post as you read it so that you can see all the Markdown code we're using.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;specialformatting&quot;&gt;Special formatting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As well as bold and italics, you can also use some other special formatting in Markdown when the need arises, for example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;s&gt;strike through&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;highlight&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;*escaped characters*&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;writingcodeblocks&quot;&gt;Writing code blocks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two types of code elements which can be inserted in Markdown, the first is inline, and the other is block. Inline code is formatted by wrapping any word or words in back-ticks, &lt;code&gt;like this&lt;/code&gt;. Larger snippets of code can be displayed across multiple lines using triple back ticks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;.my-link {
    text-decoration: underline;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to get really fancy, you can even add syntax highlighting using &lt;a href=&quot;http://prismjs.com/&quot;&gt;Prism.js&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;fullbleedimages&quot;&gt;Full bleed images&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One neat trick which you can use in Markdown to distinguish between different types of images is to add a &lt;code&gt;#hash&lt;/code&gt; value to the end of the source URL, and then target images containing the hash with special styling. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://casper.ghost.org/v1.0.0/images/walking.jpg#full&quot; alt=&quot;walking&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which is styled with...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;img[src$=&amp;quot;#full&amp;quot;] {
    max-width: 100vw;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This creates full-bleed images in the Casper theme, which stretch beyond their usual boundaries right up to the edge of the window. Every theme handles these types of things slightly differently, but it's a great trick to play with if you want to have a variety of image sizes and styles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;referencelists&quot;&gt;Reference lists&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The quick brown &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fox&quot; title=&quot;Wikipedia: Fox&quot;&gt;fox&lt;/a&gt;, jumped over the lazy &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dog&quot; title=&quot;Wikipedia: Dog&quot;&gt;dog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way to insert links in markdown is using reference lists. You might want to use this style of linking to cite reference material in a Wikipedia-style. All of the links are listed at the end of the document, so you can maintain full separation between content and its source or reference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;creatingfootnotes&quot;&gt;Creating footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quick brown fox&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; jumped over the lazy dog&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn2&quot; id=&quot;fnref2&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footnotes are a great way to add additional contextual details when appropriate. Ghost will automatically add footnote content to the very end of your post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;fullhtml&quot;&gt;Full HTML&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the best part of Markdown is that you're never limited to just Markdown. You can write HTML directly in the Ghost editor and it will just work as HTML usually does. No limits! Here's a standard YouTube embed code as an example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Cniqsc9QfDo?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;hr class=&quot;footnotes-sep&quot;&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot; class=&quot;footnote-item&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foxes are red &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot; class=&quot;footnote-backref&quot;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn2&quot; class=&quot;footnote-item&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dogs are usually not red &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref2&quot; class=&quot;footnote-backref&quot;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2017 05:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /advanced-markdown</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/advanced-markdown</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The Businessman &amp; The Fisherman</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;An American businessman took a vacation to a small coastal Mexican village on doctor’s orders. Unable to sleep after an urgent phone call from the office the first morning, he walked out to the pier to clear his head. A small boat with just one fisherman had docked, and inside the boat were several large yellowfin tuna. The American complimented the Mexican on the quality of his fish.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2014 10:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /the-businessman-and-fisherman</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/the-businessman-and-fisherman</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>A Full and Comprehensive Style Test</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Below is just about everything you’ll need to style in the theme. Check the source code to see the many embedded elements within paragraphs.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2012 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /a-full-and-comprehensive-style-test</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/a-full-and-comprehensive-style-test</guid>
      </item>
      
    
  </channel>
</rss>
